Hi everyone, today I'm going to give a
quick overview of the
course's human structure.
So in this course we're going to treat
big social data as
something more than just a
set of tools.
The core idea is that the modern social
science increasingly
depends on data that are large,
messy, and heterogenous, and often are
produced by systems that
were never built for research.
So in this first syllabus day lecture
we're going to set up a
course frame, what we mean
by social data, what comes with problems
that we've repeated
over your term two, and how
the course is organized weekly.
So I want to start with a simple claim.
The work of social data is not only
analysis, it's
everything upstream of analysis.
This course examines how social data are
created, collected,
curated, linked, validated, and
shared to scale, and under
real research constraints.
So let me make that concrete.
Suppose we see a paper with a model and
results we like, the
reliability of those results
depends on things like where the data
came from, what got
measured versus what was left
out, how missing is handled, how records
were linked, where the
units were duplicated, where
the labels were consistent, where the
whole pipeline can rerun.
So in this class we're going
to push attention upstream.
Once you're going to talk about modeling,
we're going to treat the data pipeline as
the object of methodological scrutiny.
So one core idea here, at
scale doesn't just mean bigger.
It means you start running into failure
modes that don't show up
in small project things,
and things often break
easily in these cases.
So under this
constraints, defaults matter.
The quality of the problems can become
systematic rather than idiosyncratic.
So what counts as social data?
In this course, social data includes
information about or
arising from a human interaction,
institutions, organizations, digital
platforms, text, networks,
spatial traces and sensors.
So yes, surveys and administrative
records are going to still account.
But we're also going to work with data
that came from web pages,
APIs, digitized documents,
communications and relational structures
like co-sponsorship networks or online
interaction networks.
A big reason this matters is that these
modalities come from
different assumptions.
Text data forces you to decide what
counts as a document and
how meaning is represented.
Network data forces you to decide what
counts as a time and what
the unit of analysis is.
Statial data forces you to care about
coordinate systems, aggregation
boundaries and remote
sensing measurement error.
A lot of the modern social science are
produced by platforms or
systems that are optimizing
something other than scientific validity
engagement, moderation, compliance,
things like ad revenue,
logistic efficiency.
That doesn't make them unusable.
It means we have to study them as
artifacts of the
systems that reduce them.
So here's the core
premise of this course.
First, data are constructed, not found.
Even the data feel out there.
They only become available after choices,
what to scrape, what to store, how to
parse, how to define entities,
how to code ambiguity,
which markers to exclude.
Second, measurement choices or
theoretical choices.
If we're studying polarization, your
operationalization embeds a theory about
what polarization is.
If you're studying violence, your event
definition embeds a theory
about what counts as violence.
If you're studying influence, your
network construction embeds a theory of
what influence looks like.
So third, collection decisions
shape down training influence.
Third, collection decisions
If coverage is uneven,
you don't just have noise.
You may have structural bias.
If mis-aniness is correlated with the
outcome, you don't just
lose power in that case.
You can change the sign of the effects.
If linkage error is concentrated in
certain subpopulations, you build
inequities into the dataset.
So when I say data pipelines are part of
the substantive argument, I mean if your
pipeline builds your object you study,
your pipeline is a claim about the world
and it should be open to critique.
So let me explain how
we'll run each class session.
Every session follows a consistent
structure built around
real research practice.
The goal is to connect tools, judgment,
and substantive inference about treating
methods in isolation.
So that's intentional.
In a lot of the methods
sequence, you learn a technique.
You only later see an application.
Here we're going to reverse that.
You're going to see real workflow.
We're going to learn about these tools
and then we're going
to value an application.
And there's also a deeper reason.
A lot of the hardest problems in big
social data are not how
do I run this function.
They're what decision did
I make without noticing.
So the structure, the course, the design,
the forces, the decisions that they open.
Each session is going to have a research
talk from an outside speaker.
The focus is not just on results.
It's going to be data generational
workflow, what their unit of analysis is,
how they construct the dataset,
what probe, what trade-offs they made,
and what they would do differently, and
where the inferential
vulnerabilities are.
So during these talks, I want you to
listen for a few recurring
questions during the talks.
What is the pipeline?
Not the model.
What are the fragile points?
Things like scraping linkage labeling,
geocoding validation.
What is the biggest validity threat and
how did they address it?
And what is the unknown unknown?
What might be missing entirely?
If you learn to hear research talks in
that way, you start to see that data work
is not just pre-processing stuff.
It's a major part of the
scientific contribution.
So the core of each session
is going to be a coding lab.
It's important points are the demo code
is going to be, I'm going to prepare it,
but a student is going to
a walkthrough and adapt it.
We're going to do live
execution and debugging.
We're going to
emphasize rerunnable pipelines.
The last phrase, rerunnable
pipelines, is going to be key.
The goal is not to get something to work
once on your laptop.
The goal is to build workflows that can
be rerun safely and explained clearly.
In practical terms, that means you're
going to see patterns like
saving raw data separately,
logging progress, making
code implement meaning.
So you can run it twice without
corrupting help points or capturing
environments and then
documenting your assumptions.
And importantly, we're going to treat
code as a shared research artifact.
Code is not just going
to be your personal tool.
It's a way of communicating what you did.
Reader can't understand
your code you generated.
You can evaluate your claims.
So the third component is the discussion
of an application paper
that uses the week's tools.
The goal is going to be a critical
evaluation, not a replication.
We're going to use the paper to practice
asking, how does the data
pipeline affect substantive claims?
So in the discussion, we're going to
focus on things like what are the units
and where did they come from?
What are the key measurement choices?
What are the validity
threats and how are they handled?
And would we need to
know to trust the results?
You'll notice that this course repeatedly
returns to the single meta scale,
the ability to evaluate where the data
product is trustworthy.
That skill transfers across modalities of
web data, surveys, platforms,
text networks, visual data, and machine
assisted extraction.
Now I want you to name the pipeline
stages we're going to keep emphasizing.
Acquisition, storage,
cleaning, linkage, documentation,
validation with explicit
provenance in each step.
So let me define
provenance the way we'll use it.
Provenance is the story of where the data
came from, how it was collected,
the transformations that happened, and
what limitations are known.
So you can think of provenance as the
difference between here is a CSV,
and here's a data set
that you can defend.
So you want to notice the arc here.
Acquisition and
storage are not glamorous,
but they determine whether the rest of
your work is stable.
Cleaning and linkage determine
what your units actually are.
Documentation and validation determine
whether anyone, including you,
in six months can trust the output.
So in this sense, the
pipeline is the discipline.
It forces you to create separate raw
sources from processed products.
And of course, it even makes the
transformation explicit.
So this slide is one of the most
important ideas of the course.
Tooling is methodology.
Tools shape what is
easy, hard, or invisible.
Programming language, version control,
database containers, automation,
these are so make you faster.
They make certain kinds of research
possible when other
kinds are less likely.
So for example, if you
don't use version control,
you will not have a transparent history
of analytic choices.
If you don't use a
database, when you should,
you will end up with fragile joins or a
memory or silent duplications.
If you don't capture environments, you'll
get it worked on my machine.
But failures, especially with cloud
produce, can arise from this case.
And then if you don't automate without
validation, you can scale errors.
So we're going to
repeatedly treat the tools themselves
as part of the scientific apparatus, not
because you need the newest thing,
but because you need workflows that are
inspectable and repeatable.
So modern data work requires validation
of the first-class task.
By validation, I mean sanity checks,
audits and spot checks,
intercoder reliability where relevant,
and monitoring drift and bias.
This is where big social
data can be counterintuitive.
As you scale up, you can't
manually inspect everything,
so you need systematic checks.
When your data are produced by platforms
or complex processes,
drift is normal.
So the same keyboard query might retrieve
different kinds of content over time.
Platform rules change, user populations
change, reporting practices change.
So validation isn't
something you do once in the end.
It's a practice you
embed into your pipeline.
If you learn what happened from the
course, I want you to do this.
Whenever you produce an output data set,
you should have at least a few checks
that would catch obvious problems,
so unexpected missingness, impossible
values, duplication,
shifts in distribution, and
structural breaks over time.
So this course also includes
human-in-the-loop workflows,
especially around
LLM-assisted extraction labeling.
Here's the principle. Machine assistance
does not remove judgment.
It changes what judgment looks like.
So we're going to use LLMs for a task
like structured extraction or labeling,
but humans remain responsible for
validation and adjudication
and for documenting
uncertainty and failure modes.
So the focus is
augmentation, not replacement.
We're going to be very
explicit about the risks here.
Models can be confident or wrong.
Failure can be systematic.
And you can accidentally build
a pipeline that looks precise,
but it's not trustworthy.
So the human-in-the-loop framing keeps
the scientific responsibility
of where it belongs on the researcher.
So what should you be able to do?
Right in this course, you
should be able to do four things.
First, you should be able to design a
defensible data pipeline,
not just a script, but a pipeline that
can be explained every row.
Second, you should
evaluate data quality and bias.
This means understanding
where bias enters coverage,
selection, measurement, drift from being
able to argue about its consequences.
Third, you should
reproduce an audit workflows.
That includes running
someone else's pipeline,
identifying fragile points,
and checking whether your conclusions
depend on hidden choices.
Fourth, you should be able to communicate
your limitations clearly.
A major part of the credible research is
being clear about what your data
do not capture and what
assumptions your inference requires.
So these are foundational skills.
They apply on your own work,
and they're also applied when you read
papers, review papers,
and assess evidence and policy context.
So let me close with three questions.
So first, where do you
think bias enters most often?
Is it in a collection, at labeling, at
linkage, at interpretation?
In my experience, bias often introduces
things like coverage and selection,
and it becomes very hard to fix later.
Second, which steps of a
pipeline feel least transparent?
For most people, it's the early steps,
scraping decision, parsing
rules, linkage thresholds,
exclusion criteria,
because these are the steps that really
show up in the published paper.
Third, what makes a data set or a data
product trustworthy?
If you had to evaluate the
data set you didn't build,
what would you need to see?
Would you need to say read me?
Provence notes, validation checks,
a rerunable script, version environments?
As we watch the pre-class videos and do
these labs this semester,
keep returning to that question.
What would it take for someone else to
trust the data product?
So all right, now that
we've done this framing,
this is gonna be the
format for most of our classes,
where I'll upload a video lecture
and then have a
graduate student execute code
that they adjusted from what I wrote
or from what they wrote,
and then we are going to have a brief
recap of the lecture
that they introduced and do
an in-class coding assessment.
So looking forward to
meeting you all in person.